rahulroy@outlook.com • https://in.linkedin.com/in/iamrahulroy/

Senior Software Engineer (Full Stack)

Software Engineer with **over 9 years of experience working at startups** and a strong focus on the **backend**, specializing in **Ruby on Rails & RDBMS**. **Lead hiring, training and mentoring programs**. I have managed the entire lifecycle of software from planning to execution.

Top Skills

- Ruby on Rails ~10 years of experience with Rails, at various levels of scale.
- **ReactJS** ~4 years of ReactJS experience at early to mid-size startups.
- NodeJS 1 year of experience. Migrated existing module to NodeJS microservice.
- Amazon Web Services: 3 years of hands-on experience with various AWS services like S3, SNS, SQS, Lambda, DynamoDB, etc.

Work Experience

Groove, a Clari Company - Remote

Senior Software Engineer

06/2022 - 01/2024

- As one of the two engineers in Dialer Squad, I was responsible for the end-to-end development and stability of the product.
- Led important features like Voicemail Box, and International Local Dial.
- Voicemail Box and International Local Dial helped the retention of many high ARR customers.

VueOps - Noida, India

08/2018 - 05/2022

Lead Software Engineer

- Led multiple mission-critical modules like **VueOps Drive** & **File Processing Engine** for the leading SAAS-based application in the construction industry.
- Led hiring and training efforts. Coached junior team members.
- **VueOps Drive** increased productivity and reliability significantly. Reduced over-dependency on third-party vendors.
- **File Processing Engine** made our system highly scalable & reliable. No more choking under high load.
- New File Processing Engine also reduced the cost by at least 5x. It also reduced file processing failures by 3x and helped set up good practices across the company.

Wadi - Gurgaon, India

Application Developer - Pricing

08/2017 - 08/2018

- Worked in the pricing team to automate manual tasks & improve existing processes.
- Built numerous internal applications for pricing, content and marketing team, which improved productivity by 2-5x and reduced failures/mistakes by 2x.
- Application for Pricing & Catalog team reduced manual effort by more than 1000%. The process team size was reduced from 12 to 2.

Tazzo Bikes - Hyderabad, India

Software Developer 08/2016 - 07/2017

- Worked as a lead backend developer. Created & maintained APIs for Android & iOS
- **Improved overall stability of product by** improving non-existing test coverage, and setting up staging, and pre-production environments.
- Designed & Delivered a robust payment system in a week during demonetization which helped us maintain our revenue stream & decreased the operational cost.

Freelance Ruby on Rails Developer - Remote

Full Stack Ruby on Rails Engineer

11/2015 - 08/2016

- 1. Freelance: Impcan
- Worked as full stack Ruby on Rails developer at European startup, Impcan.
- We were a team of 3 full stack developers. Impcan was supposed to be a one-stop tool for restaurants.
- 2. Freelance: India Boulevard
- Lead Backend Development for US-based Fashion Startup.
- Took the product from concept to MVP.
- Collaborated with the remote team and helped the designer and front-end developer in integrating existing designs and static applications.

Pickingo - Gurgaon, India

Software Developer

07/2015 - 11/2015

- Worked closely with CTO & CEO to create order management application for brands like Burger King, Chaayos, Subway, McDonald's etc.
- Built real-time field executive tracking systems for operation managers.

Fizzy Software - Gurgaon, India

Ruby on Rails Developer

06/2014 - 07/2015

- Responsible for handling both in-house product and service-based projects.
- Integrated 50+ SOAP & REST APIs to feed data into ElasticSearch DB for Travel Startup.
- Led development of Speedlancer(microtask platform), designed & developed payment system.

Education

Computer Science and Engineering Graduate, NIEC

Guru Gobind Singh Indraprastha University, New Delhi, India

Projects

- VueOps Drive: A document management system similar to Google Drive built using Ruby on Rails, ReactJS and AWS services. Order of magnitude faster than competitor's offering. It was able to handle high data volume.
- VueOps File Processing Engine: Migrated existing slow monolithic file processing engine to serverless infrastructure with NodeJS, AWS and Serverless framework. It was highly scalable, reliable and extremely fast. Significant reduction in the compute cost.

- Pickingo's order management and Delivery tracking Systems: Built a customer-facing order/delivery management system along with a delivery tracking system to track delivery field executives in real-time across cities. Built with Ruby on Rails, AngularJS, Redis, and AWS.
- **Groove's Dialer App**: Responsible for adding new features like international local dial, Voicemails etc to the dialer app. Also maintained the product as one of the two engineers on the squad for a Series C startup. Towards the later half the focus was on stability.
- Wadi Internal Portals for various teams: Built mission-critical internal tools for the pricing & operations team. Optimized & automated manual processes to reduce manual effort by more than 1000%. Built with Ruby on Rails, MySQL and AWS.
- TazzoBikes: I was responsible for the entire backend as the only backend engineer in the team.
 Designed & delivered a payment system in a week at an early-stage startup. Built with Ruby on Rails and MySQL.
- Other Projects like Impcan, TastyTab, Speedlancer, Data Feed Project & IndiaBoulevard
 were really important during the early phase of my career. Especially owning the entire projects
 like the Speelancer & Data Feed project as a fresh grad out of college was enriching. While
 working for a Europe-based startup like Impcan as a remote engineer with less than 2 years of
 experience made me realize the value & culture of remote organizations.

Other Important Links

GitHub: www.Github.com/iamrahulroy/
 Website: https://www.newbiedev.com/